Guide to the Abraham I. Katsh Papers MC.26
New York University Archives
Abraham I. Katsh Papers
1900-1986
1935-1970
New York University Archives
Katsh, Abraham Isaac, 1908-1998
MC.26
12.0 Linear Feet in three record cartons, one half manuscript box, and eight flat boxes
Abraham Isaac Katsh was an alumnus of New York University (NYU) and served on the faculty from 1933 until 1967, when he became the president of Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning. During his time at NYU, Katsh established the first course in modern Hebrew at an American university, and helped found the Jewish Culture Foundation. His role in creating courses in Hebrew language, culture and education led to the endowment of a chair in that field in his name. Katsh was a prolific writer and researcher and published numerous books and articles on a wide variety of topics in the field of Hebrew and Judaic studies. This collection documents Katsh's career at NYU and demonstrates Katsh's active involvement in promoting Hebrew as a course of study in American higher education in general. Materials include correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, clippings, articles, administrative files, programs, and speech notes.
Conditions Governing Access
Repository permission is required for access. Material pertaining to individual student records may be restricted in accordance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA). Please contact the New York University Archives, (212) 998-2641, university-archives@nyu.edu with specific questions regarding access to such records.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Abraham I. Katsh in 1979. The accession number associated with this gift is 85.057.
Appraisal
All NYU course catalogs and bulletins have been removed from the collection and filed with the NYU bulletins and catalog record groups.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged by material format. The correspondence has been further arranged chronologically, while the other series have not been arranged further. The collection is arranged into six series.
Series
Correspondence
Articles and Clippings
Event Files
Administrative Papers
Scrapbooks
Photographs
Biographical Note
Abraham Isaac Katsh was born in Poland on August 10, 1908, and immigrated to New York in 1925. He completed his early education in Poland and Palestine before receiving a number of degrees from New York University (NYU). Katsh received a bachelor of science from Washington Square College (1931), a master of arts from the School of Education (1932) and a doctor of jurisprudence from the School of Law (1936), all at New York University. He later completed graduate work at the Islamic Institute of Princeton University, then went on to receive a Ph.D. from Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning in Philadelphia. In 1964 Katsh received an honorary doctorate of humane letters from Hebrew Union College.
In 1933 Katsh joined the faculty of NYU and introduced the first course in modern Hebrew to be taught at an American university. He served as a lecturer, Professor of Hebrew Culture and Education, Professor of Hebrew and Near Eastern Studies, and Distinguished Professor of Research and Director of the Hebrew Institute at NYU. Among Katsh's other accomplishments at NYU were the founding of the Jewish Culture Foundation (1937) and the establishment of the NYU Library of Judaica and Hebraica. Between 1947 and 1967, Katsh also developed and directed the American Israel Student and Professorial Workshop, a summer workshop conducted in Israel and co-sponsored by the State Department and Federal Office of Education. In recognition of his contributions to the university, the chairmanship of the Hebrew Studies Department at NYU was endowed with Katsh's name in 1957. In 1967 Katsh left NYU to become the president of Dropsie College, a position he held until 1976.
Katsh was the author of numerous books, including many on Hebrew language and literature, as well as Jewish history and culture. One of his first major successes was a translation of Einstein's General Principle of Relativity into Hebrew from its original German. He later published a book entitled Judaism in Islam (1954) that explored Talmudic and Biblical influences in the Koran. In 1956 Katsh visited the Soviet Union, Poland and Hungary, where he discovered a wealth of Judaica manuscripts and documents that had been concealed from the western world since the Russian Revolution in 1917. On this trip and five successive ones, Katsh persuaded the Soviet authorities to allow him to microfilm these rare documents, including thousands of fragments from the Cairo Genizah, and to share his findings with the world. Katsh published these microfilmed images in a number of volumes, including Catalogue of Hebrew Manuscripts Preserved… (On Microfilm) in the U.S.S.R. (2 vols., 1957–58), Ginze Mishna (1971) and Ginze Talmud Bavli (1975, 1979). In 1965 Katsh published the translation of a previously undiscovered diary from the Warsaw Ghetto under the title Scroll of Agony: The Warsaw Diary of Chaim A. Kaplan. Aside from his numerous books, Katsh was also a prolific author in both Hebrew and English newspapers and academic journals.
Katsh served as a visiting scholar in the Oxford Centre for Post Graduate Hebrew Studies in 1977-78 and was also a visiting scholar at Mishkenot Sha'ananim in Jerusalem in 1978. An annual scholarship was established in his name in 1980 at the Hebrew University in Jerusalem by his former students and friends from his time at NYU.
Katsh passed away in 1998.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of the scrapbooks, researchers may only consult them with the supervision of a University archivist and must abide by all rules and regulations set forth by the archives.
Scope and Contents
The Abraham I. Katsh Papers document Katsh's career at NYU, particularly his role in founding the Jewish Culture Foundation and his work in establishing courses in Modern Hebrew language, literature and culture. The papers also demonstrate Katsh's active involvement in promoting Hebrew as a course of study in American higher education in general. Katsh's trips to the Soviet Union and his correspondence with Jewish leaders there in the 1950s and 1960s is also well documented in the scrapbooks, correspondence and articles in the collection. Katsh's early life, his time as a student at NYU, his tenure at Dropsie College and the last decade of his life are, for the most part, not included in the scope of this collection.
Jews -- Soviet Union; Hebrew language -- Study and teaching; Scrapbooks.; Israel.; Kaplan, Chaim Aron, 1880-approximately 1942; Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning; New York University. Jewish Culture Foundation; Katsh, Abraham Isaac, 1908-1998; New York University. Library of Judaica and Hebraica
- Series I: Correspondence, 1900-1986
  Conditions Governing Access
  Material pertaining to individual student records may be restricted in accordance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA). Restricted materials have been moved to separate folders within the box and are noted as restricted.
  Scope and Contents
  The "Correspondence" series is extremely comprehensive, and includes letters to Katsh from academics and notables in the field of Hebrew and/or Judaic studies, largely from Israel or America. There are also a number of letters to Katsh from representatives of the Jewish community in the Soviet Union. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1900-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1967-01-1967-04 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1967-05 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1967-06-1967-12 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series II: Articles and Clippings, 1932-1982
  The "Articles and Clippings' series consists mainly of articles written by Dr. Katsh for newspapers and scholarly journals. Articles written by others about Katsh were preserved in Katsh's scrapbooks, along with a limited amount of correspondence.
  - NYU Notebook, 1958-1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Articles, 1932-1955 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Articles, 1936-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Articles, 1936-1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Articles, 1947-1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Articles, 1948-1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Articles, 1949-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Articles, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hebrew Articles, 1949-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Articles and Clippings, 1940-1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Articles and Clippings, 1944-1956 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Articles and Clippings, 1945-1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Articles and Clippings, 1947-1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Articles and Clippings, 1949-1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Articles and Clippings, 1954-1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series III: Event Files, 1905-1985
  "Event Files" includes programs and speech notes from events at which Katsh spoke or was honored over the course of his career.
  - Event Files, 1905, 1935-1963 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Event Files, 1940-1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Event Files, 1940-1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Event Files, 1941-1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Event Files, 1942-1970 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Event Files, 1945-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Event Files, 1946-1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Event Files, 1948-1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Event Files, 1952-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Event Files, 1961-1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Administrative Papers, 1926-1983
  "Administrative Papers" consists largely of NYU publications, press releases and schedules, along with those from other organizations for the study of Hebrew language with which Katsh was involved.
  - Hebrew Language, Culture and Education Pamphlets, 1958-1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Administrative Papers, 1926-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Administrative Papers, 1930-1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Administrative Papers, 1934-1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Administrative Papers, 1942-1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Administrative Papers, 1944-1965 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Administrative Papers, 1947-1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Administrative Papers, 1950-1973 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Administrative Papers, 1953-1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Administrative Papers, 1954-1983, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Administrative Papers, 1955-1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Administrative Papers, 1956-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Administrative Papers, 1972-1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Meetings book, 1940-1953 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Series V: Scrapbooks
  The "scrapbooks" series consists of scrapbooks that Katsh created to document his career and achievements. The scrapbooks contain mostly newspaper clippings, many of which are reviews of Katsh's books, as well as a few pieces of correspondence and articles published by Katsh.
  - Scrapbook, 1949-1956 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Katsnelson Institute Scrapbook, 1949 (Box 5, Item 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1932-1946 (Box 6, Item 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1947-1949 (Box 7, Item 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1954-1957 (Box 8, Item 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1953-1954 (Box 8, Item 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1955-1956 (Box 9, Item 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1950-1952 (Box 9, Item 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1958-1959 (Box 10, Item 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Item 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1967 (Box 11, Item 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1958-1959 (Box 12, Item 1)
- Series VI: Photographs, 1947-1965, undated
  The "photographs" series contains photos of Katsh with leaders and notables in the field of Jewish and Hebraic studies, as well as Israeli politics.
  - Photographs, 1947-1965 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)